Frances Douglas papers, 1892-1963
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Frances Douglas Papers, 1892-1963
MS 037
Douglas, Frances
Contains correspondence, diaries, articles, stories, clippings, memorabilia, photographs, and translations of mostly unpublished works by Spanish-language writers. Some of the authors are Concha Espina de Serna, Vicente Blasco Ibáñez, Jose Maria Carretero, Guillermo Diaz-Caneja, Gregorio Martinez Sierra, Rafael Delgado, Pedro Juan Labarthe, Jose Lopez- Portillo y Rojas, Emilia Pardo-Bazan, Jose Echegaray and Eduardo Zamacois. Personal material consists of correspondence and family photographs, from marriage to Charles Fletcher Lummis, and later to Courtenay DeKalb, with whom she operated the Roadside Mine in Arizona. Photographs and correspondence related to the mine are present. Also included are typescripts of Douglas' published and unpublished articles, stories, and translations. Original drawings are by E.A. Burbank and Carl Oscar Borg. Correspondence with friends and publishers includes writers Eugene Rhodes, Henry Knibbs, Concha Espina, Vicente Blasco Ibáñez, José María Carretero, Pedro Labarthe, Guillermo Diaz-Caneja, and the publisher Phoebe Hearst. Diaries and photographs document travels to Mexico and Europe. Stories were recorded by Douglas while she lived among the Isleta Indians. Mexican and U.S. newspapers, 1911-1915, report on the Mexican Revolution. Related material in MS 39 and MS 297.
13 Linear Feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Author and translator Frances Douglas was born into a large family on 19 November 1870 in Milford, Connecticut; her parents were Alanson Delos Douglas and Betsy Ellen Miller. Frances attended only a few years of grammar school, and when she was sixteen, she joined her older sister Ida in Isleta, New Mexico. She began studying Spanish soon thereafter, at one point claiming that she knew "so many people who knew a little of several languages and decided [she] wanted to know all [she] could about one". Most of her knowledge of the language was self-taught, acquired from reading and from constant conversation with the Mexicans and Native Americans living in the area.
In 1891, Frances met author and activist Charles Fletcher Lummis in Isleta. Lummis was in Isleta working on behalf of the Pueblo Indians who were resisting government education program; he was also hiding from San Mateo bosses he had angered with his articles, and who had a reward on his head. [The two fell in love and had their first child, Turbesé, out of wedlock, as Lummis' divorce was not yet final.] In 1892-in a rather peculiar arrangement-Frances and Turbesé went to live with Lummis' soon-to-be-ex-wife, Dorothea, in Los Angeles until the divorce went through. The couple had four children: Dorothea (Turbesé, Lummis Fiske (1892- ), Amado Lummis (1894-1900), Jordan (Quimu) Lummis (1899- ), and Keith Lummis (1904- ). The couple had a troubled marriage, and in June 1909, Frances fled with Keith and Turbesé to San Francisco. While in San Francisco, she began a close friendship with mining engineer Courtenay DeKalb, whom she had known at least since 1908. In 1911, Frances moved to Tucson and filed for divorce from Charles Lummis, citing physical and emotional abuse and philandering. She married Courtenay DeKalb in 1913.
Frances Douglas began writing and translating Spanish authors in 1909, and published her first translation, of Vincente Blasco Ibanez's Sangre y Arena (translated title Blood and Sand), with A.C. McClurg in 1911. Her career spanned several decades, over the course of which she translated the works of many Spanish and Latin American authors including Concha Espina de Serna, José Maria Carretero, Guillermo Diaz-Caneja, Gregorio Martinez Sierra, Rafael Delgado, Pedro Juan Labarthe, José López-Portillo y Rojas, Emilia Pardo-Bazan, José Echegaray and Eduardo Zamacois. She is also credited with transcribing and translating the diary of Junipero Serra, which had been considered undecipherable. The diary was felt by many to be a fundamental document in California history. Several of her translations of Blasco Ibanez were made into motion pictures, including Blood and Sand (1922) and The Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse (1921, based on The Dead Command), both of which starred Rudolph Valentino.
With Courtenay DeKalb, Frances visited Spain twice in 1918 and 1926, on behalf of the United States Commerce Department. During these visits, in addition to her work for the government, she visited authors, organizations, and publishers. She also spent time with Concha Espina, with whom she had become close. In 1933, the University of Arizona honored Frances Douglas with an honorary doctor of letters, and in 1935 Frances Douglas became a charter member of the American Association of University Women. Between 1930-1941, she was the Associate Editor of Hispania, and remained on staff as a member of the magazine's advisory council following 1941.
Throughout the 1930s and 1940s, Frances continued to write and publish translations of her favorite authors, as well as short stories of her own. Additionally, she remained active giving speeches to various local and national women's and book clubs. In 1963, Frances Douglas and her daughter moved to San Diego, California. Prior to the move, she donated her library of 1100 books to the University of Arizona's Department of Romance Languages. Frances Douglas died in Berkeley, California in March 1969.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series.
Series I: Personal and Family Material, 1893 - 1960
Series II: Correspondence, 1893 - 1960
Series III: Manuscripts, 1909 - 1950's
Series IV: Research Files, 1904 - 1955
Series V: Photographs, 1884 - 1960
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the papers relate to Frances Douglas' life after 1911. With the exception of photographs of family and friends prior to that date, there is little information about her early life; many of the photographs of Charles Lummis are unidentified, even when he is in pictures with others who are identified. Correspondence (Series II) with family and Douglas' diaries (in Series I) provide some information regarding her early life, but not very much. The diary from 1892-1893 documents many of her daily activities in California; many of the entries are in Spanish. There is a huge gap in the diaries represented here, with the next diary dated 1910, after Douglas' relocation to San Francisco. The diaries dated 1910, 1911, and 1912 mention little about her crumbling relationship with Lummis-although there are a few brief entries regarding notice of the separation in the papers-and, equally surprising is the lack of mention of Courtenay DeKalb, whose address is listed on one of her first copyright applications, in 1908. Additionally, the early correspondence with family is equally vague on this first part of her life, as if she wished to wipe parts of it from the record (her entry in Who's Who in the West lists only her marriage to DeKalb).
However, Douglas' correspondence files for the years following 1911 is a rich resource for those interested in her work and her relationships with authors and other leading scholars of the time. As Douglas maintained a copy of her outgoing correspondence, both sides of a conversation with an author, editor, or family member are well documented. Researchers will find of particular interest Douglas' correspondence with publishers and authors, most particularly her correspondence with Concha Espina, whom she tried diligently to introduce to the American public in the same way she did with Vincente Blasco Iba?? Espina's works were not as well received in America as they were in Spain, and the letters Douglas wrote to one publisher after another on behalf of the author (and her translations from the Spanish) document her unsuccessful crusade. Additionally interesting is the correspondence regarding the Roadside Mine, near Silverbell, Arizona co-owned by Douglas and DeKalb, as well as her additional mining claims.
In Series III Manuscripts are the drafts of much of her translations as well as copies of articles, short stories, and book reviews she submitted to newspapers and magazines. In some cases, Douglas retained the copy of the work she was translating from Spanish, as well as her notes and vocabulary lists. Of interest is the copy of the American edition of Blasco Ibanez's The Dead Command, which Douglas used to note the recommended changes for the British version of her translation (unpublished). In Series IV Research Files, are Douglas' clippings on authors she translated, photographs of the authors, and clippings of stories she wished to translate. Series V Photographs, in addition to photographs of Douglas, contains a large number of photographs of the children-mostly cyanotypes-taken by Charles Lummis. Photographs of trips, other family members, and Tucson round are also included.
Douglas, Frances, 1870-1969 -- Archives.; Lummis, Charles Fletcher, 1859-1928.; DeKalb, Courtenay, b. 1861 -- Correspondence.; Knibbs, Henry Herbert, 1874-1945 -- Correspondence.; Hearst, Phoebe Apperson, 1842-1919 -- Correspondence.; Rhodes, Eugene Manlove, 1869-1934 -- Correspondence.; Blasco Ibáñez, Vicente, 1867-1928.; Espina, Concha, 1869-1955.; Borg, Carl Oscar, 1879-1947.; Burbank, E. A. (Elbridge Ayer), 1858-1949.; Carretero, José Maria, 1888-1951.; Diaz-Caneja, Guillermo, 1876-1933.; Labarthe, Pedro Juan, 1906-; American Association of University Women.; Spanish Literature -- 20th century -- History and criticism.; Isleta Indians -- Legends.; Indians of North America -- New Mexico -- Legends.; Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- Pima County -- History -- Sources.; Roadside Mine (Ariz.); Women authors.; Mexico -- History -- Revolution, 1910-1920.; 1900-1924.; 1925-1949.; Silverbell (Ariz.); Isleta Pueblo (N.M.)
Container List
- Series 1: Personal and Family Material, 1893 - 1960
  - Obituary, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Who's Who Entries, 1932 - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography of Published Works, c. 1930 - 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Passports, Lists, Calling Cards, 1898 - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Accounts, Lists, Membership, 1908-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mauretania Menus, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Las Granadas Guest Book, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Turbesé Lummis (Fiske), 1899 - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Keith & Jordan DeKalb, 1907 - 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Diaries (6), 1893 - 1926 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Diaries (9), 1921 -1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Travel Notes, 1914, 1919, 1926, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Travel Notes, [nd] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Travel Notes, 1919, [nd] (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Legal Papers Divorce, Copyright, Property, 1908 - 1941 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - List of Books in Collection, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1896 -1950, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1893 - 1960
  - Subseries 1: Family Correspondence, 1899 - 1959
    - Family, 1899 - 1915 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Family, 1916 - 1919 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Family, 1920 - 1921 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Family, 1922 - 1923 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Family, 1924 - 1925 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Family, 1926 - 1930 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Family, 1931 - 1937 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Family, 1938 - 1939 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Family, 1941 - 1946 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Family, 1947 - 1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Family, 1952 - 1955 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Family, 1956 -1959 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Family, [nd] (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Family (Fragments), [nd] (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - DeKalb, Courtenay (Includes Related Material), 1911 - 1924 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2: General Correspondence, 1893 - 1960
    - General, 1893 - 1909 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - General, 1910 - 1911 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - General, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - General, 1913 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - General, 1914 - 1918 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - General, 1919 - 1920 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - General, 1921 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - General, 1922 - 1925 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - General, 1926 - 1928 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - General, 1929 - 1932 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - General, 1933 - 1934 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - General, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - General, 1936 -1937 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - General, 1938 - 1939 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - General, 1940 - 1945 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - General, 1946 - 1949 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - General, 1950 - 1953 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - General, 1954 - 1960 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - General, [nd] (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 3: Individuals, 1900 - 1956
    - Acosta, Jose, 1927 - 1931 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Allen, Jay, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Anchondo, Antonio, 1932 -1937 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Blasco-Ibanez, Vincente, 1909 - 1919 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Blasco-Ibanez, Vincente, 1920 - 1922 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Browne, Grace H., 1938 - 1940, 1946 -1949, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Carretero, Jose Maria (2 photos), 1920 - 1926 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Coester, Albert, 1939, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Cuyas, Arturo, 1919 - 1924 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Delgado, Rafael, 1911 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Diaz-Caneja, Abelardo (4 photos, notes by Douglas), 1919 - 1933 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Diaz-Caneja, Guillermo, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Dorado,Carolina Marcial, 1927 - 1935 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Espina, Concha, 1919 - 1923 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Espina, Concha, 1924 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Espina, Concha, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Espina, Concha, 1926 - 1927 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Espina, Concha, 1928 - 1929 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Espina, Concha, 1930 - 1954, [nd] (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - De Figueroa, Augustin, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Fitz-Gerald, John D., 1929 - 1946 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Galdos, Benito Perez (authorization to translate), 1919 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Hearst, Phoebe, 1900 - 1910 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Hearst, Phoebe, 1911 - 1912 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Hearst, Phoebe (photos, clipping), 1913 - 1918 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Huntington, Archer, 1945 - 1955 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Insua, Don Alberto, 1926 - 1927 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Jáuregui, Miguel Hernandez, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Kidd, Charlotte, 1926 -1955 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Kosulich, Berenice, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Labarthe, Pedro Juan, 1920 - 1947 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Labarthe, Pedro Juan (clippings, books, photos), 1948 - 1954 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - López Portillo y Rojas, José 1911 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Machado, Antonio, 1927 - 1929, [nd] (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Más, José 1926 - 1934 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Mollenhauer, Bernhard, 1947 - 1956 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Mata, Pedro, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - De Oteyza, Luis, 1928-1929 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Paleria, Isabel Ode, 1923 - 1940 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Pereda, Clemente, 1925 - 1932, [nd] (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Pond, Florence, 1936 - 1946, [nd] (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Posada, Alfonso (authorization to translate), 1919 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Power, Victor, 1927 - 1928 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Rendueles, Roberto, 1928 - 1946 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Sandioz, Alba, 1945 - 1958 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Valles, Fred, 1941, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Van Hulse, Camil, 1940 - 1955 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Woolfolk, Wythe, 1935 - 1939 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Subseries 4: Societies, Organizations, Magazines and Publishers, 1909 - 1958
    - Hispanic Society of America (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Spanish American Atheneum (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Pan-American Union (Leo S. Rowe & Gil Borges) (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Magazines and Newspapers, 1911 - 1922 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Common Weal (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Hispania (Alfred Coester), 1929 - 1932 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Hispania (Alfred Coester), 1933 - 1934 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Hispania (Alfred Coester), 1935 - 1942 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - New York Times Book Review, 1926 - 1947 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Publisher's General, 1911 - 1939 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Appleton & Co., 1912 - 1924 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Appleton & Co., 1925 - 1934 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Appleton & Co. (Royalty Statements, Receipt Notices), 1923 - 1930 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Brentano's, 1909 - 1912 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Cine-Mondial, 1917 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Doubleday-Page & Co., 1909 - 1912 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Duffield & CO., concerning Los Muertos Mandan "The Dead Command", 1917 - 1919 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Duffield & Co., concerning Los Muertos Mandan Great Britain Version, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Duffield & Co., 1921 - 1929 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - E.P. Dunlap, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - E.P. Dutton, 1910 - 1939 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Harcourt, Brace & Co., 1921 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Houghton Mifflin & Co., 1913, 1918, 1921 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1918, 1927 - 1929 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Macmillan Company, Espina, La Esfinge Maragata (Mariflor), 1912 - June 1924 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Macmillan Company, July 1924 - 1926 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Macmillan Company, Concha Espina, 1927 - 1937 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - A.C. McClurg & Co., 1910 - 1927 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - L.C. Page & Co., 1934 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - G.P. Putnams & Sons, 1912 - 1913, 1921 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Review of Reviews, 1912 - 1915 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Small, Maynard, Rich & Co., 1921 - 1922 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Frederick A. Stokes, Co., 1916, 1921 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 5: Roadside Mine, 1912 - 1958
    - Roadside Mine, 1912 - 1921 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Roadside Mine, 1923 - 1929 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Roadside Mine, 1930 - 1935 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Roadside Mine, 1937 - 1938 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Roadside Mine, 1941 - 1945 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Roadside Mine, 1946 - 1958 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Roadside Mine, [nd] (Box 12, Folder 21)
- Series 3: Manuscripts, 1909 - 1950's
  - Subseries 1: Articles and Speeches (General), 1914 - 1950's
    - Articles, General [nd] (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Articles and Speeches: Vincente Blasco Ibanez & Concha Espina, [nd] (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Articles and Speeches, Concha Espina, 1927 - 1933, [nd] (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Articles and Speeches, Mexico, 1914 - 1916, [nd] (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Articles and Speeches, Southwest, 1916 - 1917, [nd] (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Articles and Speeches, Spain, [nd] (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Articles and Speeches, Spanish Literature & Culture, [nd] 1 of 2 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Articles and Speeches, Spanish Literature & Culture, [nd] 2 of 2 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Speeches, 1914 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Speeches, 1930's (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Speeches, 1940's - 1950's (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Speeches, [nd] (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 2: Reviews and articles for newspapers and magazines
    - Short Stories, c. 1909 - 1916, [nd] (1 of 2) (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Short Stories, c. 1909 - 1916, [nd] (2 of 2) (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Short Stories, (Isleta Indian Stories), c. 1900 - 1909 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Poetry, [nd] (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Projected Cantata (with Camil Van Hulse), [nd] (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Magazines & Newspapers, General, 1914 - 1920 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Hispania, May - Dec. 1930 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Hispania, March - Oct. 1931 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Hispania, Feb. - Dec. 1933 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Hispania, May - Dec. 1934 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Hispania, Dec. 1935 - Oct. 1936 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Hispania, Dec. 1937 - Dec. 1938, [nd] (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - New York Times Book Review, (Concha Espina's Red Beacon), 1924 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - New York Times Book Review, "Spanish Literary News", 1926 - 1927 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - New York Times Book Review, "Spanish Literary News", 1928 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - New York Times Book Review, "Spanish Literary News", 1930 - 1933 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - New York Times Book Review, "Spanish Literary News", 1934 - 1946 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 3: Translations
    - Blasco Ibanes, Vicente, Sangre Y Arena ( The Blood of the Arena) (1 of 2), 1910 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Blasco Ibanes, Vicente, Sangre Y Arena ( The Blood of the Arena) (2 of 2), 1910 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Blasco Ibanes, Vicente, Los Muertos Mandan ( Dead Command or Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse), Notebooks, 1916 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Blasco Ibanes, Vicente, Dead Command, Edited copy for British Edition, 1920 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Blasco Ibanes, Vicente, Canas Y Barro ( Reeds and Clay), 1918 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Blasco Ibanes, Vicente, La Maja Desuda, c. 1919 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Blasco Ibanes, Vicente, In El Pais Del Arte ( In the Land of Art) (1 of 2), [nd] (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Blasco Ibanes, Vicente, In El Pais Del Arte ( In the Land of Art) (2 of 2), [nd] (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Blasco Ibanes, Vicente, Misc. Notes, [nd] (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Carretero, Jose Maria La Bien Pagada ( The Broken Statue), Synopsis, 1921 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Carretero, Jose Maria La Bien Pagada ( The Broken Statue), 1921 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Del Gado, Rafael, Calandria ( The Lark of Orizaba) (1 of 2), 1912 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Del Gado, Rafael, Calandria ( The Lark of Orizaba) (2 of 2), 1912 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Del Gado, Rafael, Calandria ( The Lark of Orizaba), Copy used for translation, 1912 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Diaz-Caneja, Guillermo, Sobre en Blanco ( The Unaddressed Envelope), 1924 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Echegaray Y Eizaguirre, Jose, Mancha Que Limpia (The Cleansing Stain), 1910 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Espina, Concha, El Jayon (The Foundling), 1927 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Lopez-Portillo Y Rojas, Jose, Maria Delas Nieves ( The Mezcal Maker), [nd] (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Lopez-Portillo Y Rojas, Jose, Maria Delas Nieves ( The Mezcal Maker), Notebooks, [nd] (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Lopez-Portillo Y Rojas, Jose, The Lottery Ticket, [nd] (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Lopez-Portillo Y Rojas, Jose, La Horma de su Zapeto and Un Drama de Tres Horas, [nd] (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Lopez-Portillo Y Rojas, Jose, A Mexican Badman, [nd] (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Martinez-Sierra, Gregorio, El Agua Dormida ( Sleeping Waters), [nd] (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Martinez-Sierra, Gregorio, Tu Es La Paz ( Thou Art Peace), c. 1920 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Pardo Bazan, Emilia, The Capital Prize, [nd] (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Zamacois, Eduardo, Lo Pasado ( The Eternal Triangle), 1912 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Pan American Patriots, [nd] (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Poetry, [nd] (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Short Stories, [nd] (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified, [nd] (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Series 4: Research Files
  - Blasco Ibanez, Vincente, Clippings, letters, etc., 1909 - 1928 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Blasco Ibanez, Vincente, 1915 - 1923, [nd] (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Borg, Carl Oscar, 1904 - 1949, [nd] (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Espina, Concha, Biographical note, c. 1924, 1933, [nd] (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Espina, Concha, Clippings, 1921 - 1927, [nd] (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Espina, Concha, Research material, miscellaneous, 1923 - 1945, [nd] (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Espina, Concha, Photographs, 1922 - 1929, [nd] (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Knibbs, Henry Herbert & Eugene Manfield Rhodes, 1922 - 1955, [nd] (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Valles, Frederico, 1934 - 1947, [nd] (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous biographical material, [nd] (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Spanish stories for translation, [nd] (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - La Maja Vestida 1919 (Box 20, Folder 7)
- Series 5: Photographs, 1884 - 1960
  - Subseries 1: Frances Douglas, c. 1890 - 1960
    - Douglas, Frances, c. 1890's - 1910 (Box 21, Folder 1)